all right everybody we are live it is
jack murphy this is jack murphy live
this is the jack murphy live podcast you
can find me jack murphy
on youtube jack murphy live on twitter
jack murphy live the website
what do you know jackmurphylive.com the
book is
democrat to deplorable get that on
amazon
and if you're interested in our all
men's community check us out at
liminalhyphenorder.com my guest today
is a repeat offender on the jack murphy
live podcast
it is alan bukhari he is the breitbart
news senior technology correspondent and
author of the latest book deleted big
text battle to erase the trump movement
and steal the election allen how are you
doing sir it's great to have you back on
the podcast today hi jack good to see
you
yeah good to be back likewise i
appreciate it thank you for making the
time today
uh you have been working on these
stories and in this field and on this
beat for some time now
and since you are a repeat uh guest on
jack murphy live we'll refer
people back to that for the sort of
personal backstory but i do want to just
sort of get caught up on
how did you come to be so passionate or
interested
in this subject area i know that the
road for me
to writing a book was a long one it was
personal i had something i had to say
what was it what was it for you that
brought you to this subject which is
truly one of the most important things
going on in the world today
especially for people like me especially
for people like you
tell me what was it that motivated you
on this story and on this beat here
well you know i sort of you know i was
i'm a mid millennial so i grew up with
the internet the internet was my entire
childhood and teenage years and the
internet as i remember it was you know
very free-wheeling open
place you could go on the internet speak
your mind
and encounter very little censorship
this was the great technology of the
millennial generation
it should have been a crowning
technological achievement of mankind
never
before in human history were people able
to simply just
use you know have a device turn it on
and suddenly have access to a global
audience that was very new that's a
that was an unprecedented level of free
speech
but instead of celebrating it uh the
establishment has worked overtime for
the past five years
to take it away and i saw that coming
even before the even before the trump
movement even before
the panic and the freak out in silicon
valley over that
um you know much as you experienced uh
you know people trying to cancel you and
ostracize you
um silicon valley offers
the greatest amount of power for the
left to do that we know the left today
they want to ostracize people they want
to cancel people who
disagree with the narrative and there's
no better way to do that than getting
the kicked off social media which is
increasingly essential to having a
platform
to running a business to running a
political movement
to anything you can imagine it's an
awesome amount of power and it's
completely unregulated
and uncontrolled so it's it's that's why
we're seeing what we're seeing it's been
such a tempting target for the left
because it's so powerful
yeah indeed and you bring up a great
point the social media platforms aren't
just about
talking about your cats or sharing
pictures of your friends or even just
spewing
whatever political nonsense you want to
spew more and more
there's no even distinction between
business or online business
or life and online life or organizing in
real life or organizing online
it is a hundred percent essential to
have access to these services in order
to pretty much do anything these days if
you're not
online you're basically zero you're
basically dead
and that is the way that some people
feel when they get canceled i'll tell
you when
when uh when twitter had its bug like
you know had its glitch or whatever it's
attacked just like three or four days
ago
and the whole thing was down i was on
the website and i'm trying to type in a
tweet and it says oops something went
wrong oops something went wrong
check my notifications no notifications
nothing in my feed and i'm like well
this is how it ends huh just like
silence you have no access no nothing i
thought i had got got
at that point it took it took a few
minutes and i'll tell you the feeling
that i had
was not a good one man it was uh it was
like a pit
in my stomach and you know it's like
yeah you know
you're not the only one i got a call
from a friend that saved death
uh wondering oh no i've been heated from
social media is this the head
it just shows you how how much we depend
on these platforms and how they can just
take it away
at the drop of a hat with a push of a
button um
there's a chapter in this book um the
one on facebook that talks about how
there was this website called little
things not a political website it was
a political it was all about you know
viral pictures of cats and you know
other
family-friendly internet content did
very well by using facebook
to disseminate his content had 100
employees facebook comes along and makes
an algorithm change targeted at the
right by the way
in uh in i believe 2018 start of 2018
and immediately that website goes
back essentially essentially bankrupt
defunct had to fire all their employees
and shut down
and facebook gave them no warning they
just suddenly changed their algorithms
so this is the position that uh
even a lot of non-political businesses
are in right now
uh it's it's totally crazy i mean
physical landlords aren't allowed to do
this a physical land will kind of throw
you out of your storefront
uh because they don't like what you're
saying about politics you could sue them
if they did
uh but we but uh online businesses have
no uh
no recourse and no due process at all i
try and make this point as often as
possible because it goes beyond
politics uh everyone is at the mercy of
these tech giants whether you're a
democrat republican or just not even
political at all
yeah even if your business is just
selling cat toys or whatever you have to
be online you have to have access to
people you have to be able to
communicate
and i think that this brings up one of
the more overarching discussions in your
book and all about
social media censorship and and the tech
sort of dark knight that is being
brought upon us
is that you know when social media
started
you know when twitter started it was
just 140 characters little text messages
people chatting with each other but it's
become so much more than that and it's
it's through its market power has
evolved into being a different sort of
entity than just your private chat
channel can you describe and maybe use
the analogy you used in the book
about sort of fedex shipping your
packages etc like i thought that was a
really great way to understand what's
happened here
yeah so i opened the book as you say by
uh asking the readers like imagine
themselves in
you know in the 1960s before the
internet uh suddenly your typewriter
stops working because you're posting
hate speech
your phone line cuts you off and the
postal service refuses to carry your
mail
it sounds bizarre but that's that's the
world we're currently living in with
these tech giants they're doing exactly
the same thing and uh look at the
example of gab i talked about this in
the book as well
uh gab simply wanted to do what twitter
was doing in you know 2008 2009
when it had basically no restrictions on
legal constitutionally protected speech
uh they even allowed you know the arab
spring to you know encourage violent
uprising
uh across the middle east so this was
this was an open free platform gab
wanted to do the same thing
but uh in the in the present day in the
current year that's not allowed so what
happened was
the google app store kicked them off the
apple app store
kicked them off uh and you know you'll
remember google and apple control
99 of all smartphone operating systems
worldwide that's the entire
smartphone market uh you can still
technically get on google
uh phones uh you know through a very
complicated process downloading app
through your browser and so forth
beyond the technical ability of a casual
users uh but that's effectively
excluding them from all smartphones
so that's what happens when you try and
create a competitor uh
to these platforms the uh it's like if
you try to
create a competitor to uh to the postal
service and the uh the road said okay
your postal trucks aren't allowed uh
we're only going to allow the uh
the mailing service that bans hate
speech that's essentially what's going
on with the app stores
uh so it's it's a totally bizarre
situation when you compare it to
previous forms of communications
whether it's you know the post uh phones
or typewriters
uh we're in a situation where the
primary means of communications
can be cut off from us at a moment's
notice if the owners of the platforms
don't like what we say
yeah and it didn't start off like this
right it started off as something new
and fresh and something on the fringe
for edge users and and first movers
early adopters etc it started off fun
and then things you know evolved and it
became you know people understood the
power of it and then it became more
powerful
itself and so the services that they
offer have actually gone through a
transformation in both their intent
their execution and their impact on the
world
and because of that has the way that our
government
should view them is the way that we as
citizens should view these social media
companies these tech companies
has it changed has their status changed
i'm sort of teeing you up here to talk
about
section 230 i honestly don't have a
strong grasp on what all that means
precisely
uh so maybe you could help us understand
a little bit about that because
we have to have a change of perspective
on the social media companies in order
for us to
affect the change that we need in order
to protect everybody right so
what is section 230 what protections do
they have right now
how can they go about doing this stuff
is there anything on the horizon
that could change that help us
understand what that means
uh okay well i'll make this one point
this is not a partisan point this is the
honest truth
there's literally only one powerful
politician in the country today who
could actually do something about big
tech and he's doing something about big
that's donald trump the establishment
republicans are doing nothing
the democrats don't want to do anything
in fact the democrats want to use their
power to push for even more censorship
they've said so again and again biden
said that the only person doing
something is donald trump he passed an
executive order on the subject
we saw the fcc chairman ajit pai uh
when the new post thing happened last
week saying okay we're going to look at
rule making changes for section 230
that happened because donald trump
passed his executive order
pai was responding to a petition drafted
by someone called adam kandaya
who's a free speech law professor who
actually sued twitter and free speech
cases in the past and the megan murphy
case actually might be familiar with
that
he was appointed to the administration
by donald trump
he then drafted that petition that went
before the fcc
uh that allowed a g pai to make that
statement donald trump's
also um sounding like a surrogate here
but this is like literally the only
positive thing that's happening at the
moment
he also you know nominated nathan
simmington the fcc someone who's very
good on the social media censorship
issue
or so i hear uh just compare that for a
moment to the establishment republicans
today they announce they're actually not
going to subpoena
jack dorsey not because the democrats
don't want it but because a few
republicans on the
on the senate judiciary committee were
wavering uh so twitter literally
censored america's oldest newspaper the
new york post a newspaper founded by
alexander hamilton they can't even
muster
the political unity to subpoena jack
dorsey the new york post by the way is
still locked out of their twitter
account as we speak
uh they've been locked out for five days
and we are
less than two weeks from the election
this is insane this is obvious election
interference
and this has been we've been we've known
about what they're doing for five years
now i've caught them red-handed on so
many occasions
i can't even count the number of leaks
from google and facebook exposing
censorship that i published in breitbart
news
we we know about this and the
republicans still can't even
subpoena jack dorsey so uh honestly the
only uh
the only person at the moment you can
rely on to do something about this is
donald trump
before we go past that i want to use
this opportunity as a chance to point
something out
i'm often talking here about networks
and
emergent networks and network politics
and network tribalism and then we just
see that there are these various groups
we've got the blm
antifa groups we've got the corporations
the establishment the insurgency which
is the trump
maga movement because that is an
insurgent movement against both
the establishment gop and the democrats
the uniparty the corporate uniparty
cabal
and i tell people that blm antifa and
the corporations have alignment right
now people like how is that even
possible
and the reason is this the establishment
republicans and the democrats are so
afraid or don't wanna or so in the
pockets
of the corporations that they are not
taking any serious action on antitrust
on corporate collusion on price fixing
on market manipulation on censorship on
any of these matters and because of that
there is now an alignment between blm
antifa and the corporations that you can
see obviously
every day when the corporations not only
send money to black lives matter they
hang their banners over their buildings
they allow
they do advertising and messaging for
blm
and donate billions of dollars etc etc
and in talking to matt stoller
and reading matt soler's book goliath it
comes to it becomes all very perfectly
clear
that the corporate party the uniparty
the establishment gop and the democrats
are
in cahoots with the corporations and
they're all
on one side whereas the insurgent maga
trump movement
is the only one trying to fight any of
this stuff and when you say that trump
is the only one doing anything you're
absolutely right
but i will say my criticism trump this
might be a little too
a little too little a little too late we
should have done this two years ago the
election has been impacted by
his inaction which i don't understand
and i'm glad that things are moving now
but i wanted them to move more quickly
with more force and more direction
but it's very difficult the forces are
very entrenched the money is very big
the committees are
are co-opted etc etc so
that's a point for my listeners
long-time listeners so you can really
understand that so what are we doing
right now what is it yeah go for it
okay i just want to take a massive
tangent based on what you just said
uh first of all i totally understand
what you just said uh you know why was
there so much inaction
uh that was very frustrating in the
early years of the trump movement the
trump
administration sorry and that was
because the federal bureaucracy was
totally co-opted
and uh to be fair the uh the personnel
office which is the crucial office of
the white house that
determines staffing in the federal
bureaucracy that should have been
staffed with a trumper
from day one instead it was stopped by
an establishment republican that only
changed
uh the start of this year with the
appointment of john mcintyre he's uh
that's that staffing change was critical
because that's allowed the
administration to finally get the right
people in those posts
to take action on the issue i just want
to take a tangent based on what you just
said because it's
it uh it ties to something i saw the
other day on twitter which is very
interesting someone comparing the
present situation of
uh the american republican the uh the
american republic
to the late roman republic and uh this
is something this is a comparison that's
made a lot by sort of
uh uh people who think america is in
decline that american democracy is in
decline
that you've got a similar situation
where the senate
the representative body is completely
co-opted by special interests
doesn't work for the people and
increasingly the only uh
the only body that the people can
believe represent their interest is the
executive branch
uh so it's almost like if we want social
media to serve the people and not
serve special interests and not just
censor everyone and
delete people's livelihoods you have to
turn to the executive branch you have to
give more power to the executive branch
which of course so you can see the
analogy to rome there uh increasingly
powerful executive
uh increasingly corrupt and hated
legislature so moving away from the uh
representative democracy and more to
like an imperial
executive but that's really what we're
seeing with the tech issue the tech
giants have completely co-opted
washington dc they flooded both
republicans and democrats
with money uh they're the biggest lobby
expenditures now there'll be a whole
chapter from
him deleted on this uh in the book when
uh silicon valley met washington dc
they've completely taken over
establishment
uh conservative think tanks completely
taken over congress
uh that's why it's so difficult to get
anything through congress that's why the
executive branch which is
the least affected by it by uh by
lobbying spending i think at the moment
anyway uh
is the only body that's really taking
serious action on this
historical analogy yeah it's a great
analogy and
and it's important for people to
understand yeah we're being critical of
trump but also remember this donald
trump was a weapon he was a
high speed weapon a maneuver weapon
that moved quickly was an insurgent got
behind enemy lines pretty much and then
took over and so because he was like an
expeditionary force he was out there all
by himself
and he wasn't dragging a massive
operation with him he wasn't dragging a
huge bear actually with them
we haven't even gotten to this sort of
for
a lack of a better uh analogy we haven't
gotten to the nation building stage yet
of this takeover right and it's taking
time like
first you get into office you have to
learn how to do the office no one has
ever been president before when they
become president you got to figure that
out
and especially when you're an outsider
you're coming in basically to enemy
territory
i interviewed amanda milius last night
and we talked all about the plot against
the president i mean not only did he
come
without an established bureaucracy with
him but he came into
a hostile environment where everybody
was trying to take him out and everybody
was trying to ruin
the administration and chop them off at
the feet and then hang
them in front of everybody and so we're
seeing now
like as as you learn how to run the
country and learn how to do bureaucracy
and institution building
we're seeing evidence that that is
growing and getting a little bit more
powerful
so yes there's a criticism but also
there's just the reality of what was
happening
and hopefully in term two we will see
some more of this institution building
and more of a takeover of the
these deep state entities basically that
are controlling
the entire conversation so if there's
any uh future presidents listening
to this uh this show uh the crucial
office is called the personnel office
the white house ppo
you control that you control the
bureaucracy that's what trump did not do
at the start
but he has done so now there's a trump
loyalist there
um but yeah that's the critical office
if you don't control personnel you don't
control policy
right yeah personal is policy policy is
personnel i don't know there's a
there's a cliche in there somewhere so
let's talk a little bit about 230. i
don't know are do you feel like you can
explain that to me because
absolutely there's so many people
competing and yapping on both sides
libertarians say it's this thing over
here democrats say this i don't think
most people have any freaking clue what
it really means
so let's talk about that for a minute
what is social media is it a utility
what is 230 are they publications are
they
produced like what is tell us what it is
so here's the issue with social media
platforms or we need any
uh any online like a search engine as
well
in in order to host you know all the uh
all the websites on google
or in order to host all the videos of
youtube or the posts on twitter and
facebook
or instagram or any of these platforms
it's impossible for social media
platforms to be legally liable so if you
could
if you could sue twitter for post people
make on twitter
twitter's business model would not be
viable so they need a special law called
section 230
that renders them immune from those
lawsuits uh it also renders them immune
and i think this was this was never
really uh necessary
for the platform in the same way that
the first legal immunity was
they're also immune from lawsuits under
that law for taking down content
uh so i kind of understand why that need
to be immune from lawsuits arising from
you know
defamation or illegal content even
posted by their users because you know
how do you how do you police millions
and billions of posts
uh you've got to hold the users liable
for those not the platforms otherwise
you can't have the platforms
uh but i don't see why they should be uh
immune from lawsuits
around taking down content because they
don't have to take down
any legal constitutionally protected
content when you think about it
they could just uh give users the
ability to filter on their own
and google has done this google has a
button it's had a button for i think
decades now safe search you can turn
that button on if you want to filter out
of scene search results from google
and that's up to the user it's not up to
google you decide whether you want to
turn that button on or off
they could very easily provide a similar
button for so-called hate speech or
so-called misinformation so-called fake
news
all the other categories that they've
invented to filter legal
constitutionally protected speech
they could turn that over to the users
give them a similar button to turn on or
off
the reason why they haven't is because
they care more about political power
today than they care about consumer
choice
and you know my sources in facebook and
uh google who've spoken me to the book
you know spoke
spoken to me for the book sorry they say
that the story was the same in every
single company in every single tech
giant google facebook
twitter complete panic after the trump
election
what do we do about it how did we let
this happen
and an immediate focus on things like
misinformation and disinformation
and all the initiatives they set up
right after the election by the way it's
very obvious what they're doing this is
all right after the election
uh to curtail that's the uh the trump
movement
uh but to go back to section 230 i went
on a tangent there
but to go back to section 230 if you
say that a platform has to behave in a
certain way in order to be a platform
what you can do is uh basically you're
telling these tech companies that
if you don't adhere to the standards of
being a platform like remaining
politically neutral
or allowing users to opt out of any
filter you create that's
i think a standard that should be
applied across the industry by law
if you don't do that then you lose your
legal immunity because without that
legal immunity
they can't operate as platforms their
business model falls apart
and uh many libertarians and free speech
defenders will come in and say well look
these these companies they have first
amendment rights like everyone else
therefore they should be allowed to take
down whatever they want censor whoever
they want
uh but here's the thing yes every
company does a first amendment right but
not every company has these special
legal immunities
so it's very reasonable to say that uh
if you want these special privileges
that no other type of company
gets then you have to behave in a
certain way you have to be the type of
company you say you are
otherwise you're not getting the legal
immunities that are for those specific
types of companies
so when you have a platform censoring
and
editing the argument is that platform
should be considered a publisher
they should be liable for all the
content posted by their users
um i think when you make that clear in
the law
or when uh the fcc gets gets involved
and does a rule making change
you have to say if you're filtering
legal content constitutional
content on behalf of your users and not
simply giving them the option to filter
that content themselves
then you are no longer a platform then
you don't get section 230
protections i think that will go a long
way to fixing the issue
yeah what's interesting about this is
that people are like oh we don't want
more regulation
oh free speech shouldn't be regulated
whatever but there's actually more than
one kind of regulation there's
regulation
of the companies but then there's sort
of like regulation of the laws
and in this case we're already
regulating the laws by offering them up
a special immunity it's very similar to
the antitrust exemption that
professional sports league get which
opened them up to actual
that's regulating the government but it
actually opens them up to a little bit
of regulation themselves and in this
case
they're already being regulated this
market is already being regulated
there's already special rules in place
to allow the market to exist adding a
couple more
isn't like changing the off the playing
field altogether
it's just refining the process that's
already in place
because this is a new thing like social
media is a new
thing this is a unforeseen technology it
has
unforeseen power it holds a special
place in
in american culture economic society
politics technology everything
and because of that there should be a
little extra oversight and we're
we haven't we haven't gotten it in the
right direction in fact all the sort of
oversight over the speech
and such has been coming from the social
media companies themselves
and you alluded to it uh just now in
terms of the panic
and this is where i want to like kick
off sort of uh going you know talking
about the arguments in the book
you know it wasn't like this really in
right i mean it was the wild west it was
the wild west out there there's no
question about it even in 2015
even in 2016 but then the election
happened and
talk us about the panic right this the
panic that that took over
all of social media silicon valley
technology
what happened in 2016 we know the answer
but how did they react and what did they
do
so uh yeah so there's a chapter in the
book called the panic and it explains
that when you when you're trying to
censor something especially the internet
which
was created as this kind of
anti-censorship idea a lot of people
believed in that especially in silicon
valley
you've got to create a kind of moral
panic first in order to control
something first you have to get enough
support from society
from the public to control what you're
trying to control and that's what they
did with the internet uh
so many ways that they did this you know
that the russian disinformation the
russian propaganda
element uh the idea that social media is
is corrupting us it's making a so-called
hyper partisan
uh that is leading to the breakdown of
society they even blamed facebook for
causing genocides
and you know racial killings in uh in
southeast asia
uh so you you name it they were throwing
everything at these social media
companies saying that
and the underlying message was if you
allow an open free internet if you don't
take control of your platforms
if you don't take responsibility they
love that word they love calling the
silicon valley ceos irresponsible uh for
not censoring that platform if you don't
do that then you're literally causing
genocide
that was there the argument they made
and the thing i get into in the book
which is so interesting i think
and what i found maybe the most
interesting of those research in the
book is that this has happened so many
times before
with every advance in communications
technology
every time throughout history where more
power to communicate and spread your
message
uh has sort of devolved down from elites
to the masses every time there's been a
similar panic
so the at the end of the 19th century
when uh
literacy was just happening when there
was suddenly mass literacy in europe
uh when the costs of printing were going
down when there was a
the rise of the telegraph we saw the
rise of all these you know
new popular forms of newspapers you know
there were newspapers before that but
they were all targeted at the elite
because in many
in many cases across europe the elite
class was the only class that could read
this completely changed at the end of
the 19th century and as soon as we get
these new mediums
popular newspapers uh popular literature
mass market literature
there was a panic alongside uh that came
along with it they called the new
newspapers yellow journalism
uh that was the uh that was the fake
news term of the day the disinformation
term of the day called yellow journalism
and most amusingly they called uh joseph
pulitzer
and uh and william randolph hurst who
are titans of the news industry you
couldn't get more respected names today
they called them purveys of a yellow
journalist because they were publishing
uh
newspapers for the masses rather than
newspapers for the elites
uh so every time throughout history this
has happened it happened with tv as well
they said tv is causing violence it's uh
leading to the erosion of democracy
because people aren't getting involved
they aren't getting interactive they're
just staring at their screens
that was the argument in the post-war
period funnily enough
uh the argument with social media is now
the complete opposite uh they're arguing
we're too interactive
we're getting hyper partisan we're
getting too involved so it's like you
can't win
uh the general message of that chapter
is that
whenever more there's a new
communications medium
or whenever there's um
the more ability for the air for the
more communication for the masses and
not elites there's always a panic that
goes along with it
and i think this panic over social media
is the biggest one of all because elites
have seen that this particular medium
threatens them in a way
that uh even you know the expansion of
mass-market newspapers didn't even the
way that tv didn't in fact tv was kind
of helpful for the elites because it put
power in the hands of a few
ultra wealthy um executives who could
afford to have big studios
social media is the opposite all you
need is a laptop to access a global
audience
uh yeah what's interesting is it's
always about power right this is always
about power it's about the elites trying
to hold on to their power in this case
right
it's always about power and i think
maybe the most scary quote in the book
there's lots of quotes from silicon
valley insiders that are very scary you
can get into those you know
how how much of the censorship is
invisible but an even scarier quote i
think came from a guy who i talked to
inside the government and uh he's been
following
social media censorship for a long time
and
the way he put it was western elites
uh actually supported online free speech
throughout the obama years
uh with in the in the early rise of
social media because the way they saw it
social media was a very
useful tool for uh for destabilizing and
uh regime changing countries abroad that
they didn't like whether it was you know
arab dictatorships or eastern european
governments
uh they saw social media as a kind of
weapon to spread their influence
but he said with the rise of brexit with
the rise of donald trump with the rise
of all these
movements that came out of nowhere and
took the establishment in
uh in the west completely by surprise he
said
they panicked and suddenly realized that
the same tools used to
destabilize and regime change abroad
could regime change the establishment
here at home
um interestingly today you'll see the
most
strong the most strident and organized
uh and relentless force pushing for
internet censorship
is uh not even the left obviously
they're very much in favor but it's all
these
sort of foreign policy ngos that have
set up these disinformation campaigns
you know
darren b he talks about this the whole
color revolutions establishment
uh just the other day at breitbart news
published an art about the german
marshall fund the german marshall funds
main main areas of focus
are you know eastern europe ukraine
black sea all of these
areas that are very um uh have a very
high focus for the western foreign
policy establishment
but they're also doing stuff on
disinformation and they just published a
report saying that social media
platforms should
uh apply friction which is their word
for suppress
uh fox news breitbart news all of
conservative media basically for being
deceptive
so uh foreign policy elites who by the
way span
as we were saying they span both parties
you know their democrats and their
republicans
uh the establishment they are really the
most relentless force pushing for social
media censorship at the moment
there is an argument to be made that
social media is destabilizing so in the
old days in the days of the blue
church we had top-down information
distribution we had walter cronkite
telling everybody what to believe
while they were eating dinner he was at
the desk teaching us all
the universities we have teachers at the
front of the classroom teaching the
masses what to believe and what to think
and what we've seen now or that built
that built a social cohesion it really
did we were all sort of pulling on the
same rope as it were to steal
a cliche from baseball uh but then
social media comes and now we've had
sort of an explosion i've called it like
a big bang explosion actually where
everything has just been
spit out into the universe and now
certain areas are picking up gravity and
attracting more mass and attracting more
power
and what that means is that there
instead of one story for us all to
believe
there's now a million stories for a
million different people to believe
and that does actually have an
inherently destabilizing effect on
national cohesion
and it does provide the the sort of
the the petri dish in which your network
tribalism
can arise now is that is that in of
itself something worth stopping
no i mean that is us you know sort of
using the market to come to
our uh a market you know decided version
of truth or reality or good or bad or
right or wrong
and it does allow for voices that until
now voices that had been
uh silenced to have to have a voice it's
given an opportunity for somebody like
me to reach an audience tens of
thousands sometimes millions of people
to get this information out there but i
do see from the other side their
argument that they need
from their personal viewpoint how they
need to maintain power
and that's what they want to do so
they're scaring the bejesus out of
all of us there's a moral panic just as
there's been
going all the way back to the printing
press and everything else
and they're using it to scare us so they
can take more control and more power
over ourselves you know actually just
just briefly
i don't think it's like a conspiracy
that they plan this i think they
themselves are legitimately terrified
which is why everything they're saying
sounds terrified and seems intended to
scare us
it's because they're terrified because
they're losing their power they're
losing their control over information
they're seeing all these unusual uh
movements they didn't expect rise up to
change them and
they all all these movements say you
know we hate the elites and get rid of
the elites but these guys are the elite
so they would be scared
right exactly right and so they've
they've taken
the social media power they've turned it
into a moral panic they've amplified the
moral panic
they're using it to censor and control
people the trump election scared the
hell out of all these people you
broke an amazing story a couple years
ago where we had
live video recording of like a
company-wide meeting with the head
c c level executives at google
basically crying up on stage saying that
the trump election was the worst thing
that they ever saw they're going to do
everything that they can do
to stop it and to prevent it from
happening again and i do believe another
tangent here
that that sentiment of like we have to
stop this and
or we have to never let it happen again
that sentiment is just
burbling underneath all the democrats
all the left right now and they're
chomping at the bit
to get elected to get into power so that
they can begin a truth and
reconciliation period
which is really code for like lies and
capitulation and torture and torment and
exile they're going to come after
everybody so that they can in their
words
make sure this doesn't happen again so
it's something that we need to be really
worried about
and i'm happy to see at least trump
taking some action now that may
hopefully even extend after
this term but again we would have liked
to see
a little bit more a little bit sooner
one personal story i have
uh and relates to this and we're going
to talk about how they'd cover things up
through over
versus covert actions one of one thing
that happened to me
a few months ago and it happened to
breitbart and federalists and a bunch of
other people at the same time
i was just doing a regular name search
for my website just to check
see how the standings were and where i
was ranking and usually i type in jack
murphy live
into google all my stuff comes up right
at the top all my articles
jackmurphylive.com all that
but this time man literally nothing from
my website came up
even when i searched quotes
jackmurphylive.com quote
nothing from my website came up so i i
contacted my tech guy
and he's been on web doing seo and
search and stuff for two decades so he
knows what's up
we're digging into it we're looking at
it we're searching we're looking
we're comparing it to bing where all my
stuff comes up and bing no problem
and as we're doing the tests
the next search we do one search there's
nothing the next search we do it's
all back it's all back like a switch
flipped
like they turned it back on like it was
a test run or something and i go onto
twitter and i'm like hey i'm being
censored and then all of a sudden that
afternoon
boom breitbart federalists everybody
saying the same exact thing so
let's talk about that that is a is that
covert or is that over
and then let's leave this into the
covert versus overt discussion do you
know about that i think
well i think it's it's semi cover
because not something that they
announced or something that they told
people about
uh so there's although they were hoping
people wouldn't notice obviously uh you
noticed breitbart news notice you know
we did a big story about this back in uh
july show and i think it was 99
reduction in visibility for breitbart
newslink since
uh compared to 2016. so it was like they
turned off
they obviously flipped the switch um and
again like like uh you you know we had
seo experts looking at this and telling
us how it was all going down and you
know
that was 99
on on the world's largest uh search
engine by the way there's a search
engine that itself controls 90
of all searches worldwide um so yeah
as as to whether it's covert or over
it's not as covered as some of the
things silicon valley is doing but it's
um
it's uh only covered if you it's only uh
oh but if you notice it
so how long this was going on before
people noticed
right exactly right and then the switch
flipped and then everything was back
and so let's talk about this there
there's the panic they're covering
things up
and they use two different avenues to
use over versus covert let's get an
example of what's over and an example of
what's covert
the covert [ __ ] might even be the
scariest part of all
the stuff about dr epstein we can talk
about that so you know what what is
what are they doing what is covert
versus over how are they deleting us
so there are a few concepts that need to
be understood to really understand the
the covert
censorship so there's a chapter in the
book chapter six that talks about how
algorithms are used to censor and every
silicon valley platform there's google
facebook twitter youtube you name it
what determines what appears at the top
of your feed or does it have to sort
through millions and millions of
information
um what determines that is a type of
score
every platform uses a uh what's called a
some some some of the platforms call it
the quality ranking other platforms use
different terminology
but everything you post is given a
numerical value that determine where you
are in the pecking order that determine
whether you're
if they're at the top of people's
facebook feeds or whether you're never
gonna be seen there at all
whether you're on page one of google or
page 100 of google where people will
never find you
uh i think 90 of people don't go beyond
the first
uh page of google it's a maybe maybe 90
maybe 70
it's a very high number uh so that's
determined by a numerical value
and it used to be the case that uh the
criteria
used to give your content that score was
pretty objective so
by objective i mean you're not
politically motivated in any way but
things like you know
are you posting malware are you posting
websites with viruses or illegal content
is your content relevant is it timely is
it popular are lots of people sharing it
those are the things that you used to
determine what would go at the top of
your feet and also they use you know
data as well you know these companies
basically spy on everyone to find out
what their interests are so the
algorithms
also ask well is this relevant to that
particular user's interests and that
determines what's going to go at the top
of your feed
so say you're a huge baseball fan if
they find a really popular post about
baseball
they're not going to send that to a
football fan but they might put at the
top of a baseball fan speed
so pretty non-political criteria but
obviously ever since
2016 uh you know my sources who work for
the companies say this
and the companies themselves say it
openly they're introducing
all sorts of new criteria like
disinformation is
is the website or the account posting
disinformation is it posting hate speech
conspiracy theories is the link
authoritative
or does it come from an authoritative
source what is authoritative what's
non-authoritative
this is these are the type of things
they're now training their algorithms
to recognize and that will now go into
your
quality ranking or whatever else they
call these secret scores
you can't see your score completely
hidden from you by the way it's
basically silicon valley social credit
score because
while it used to be determined by a
non-political criteria it now
essentially what it does is ranks you
based on conformity to silicon valley's
values and how is it any different from
what china is doing
it's not different at all um two other
concepts that need that people need to
understand are network analysis
and language analysis
language analysis you know pretty
straightforward it's how machines
recognize language
so training an algorithm to recognize
hate speech that's language analysis
but to train an algorithm to recognize
hate but you have to give it a bunch of
data and say this is hate speech
this isn't hate speech and that's how
you train it to make more accurate
judgments in fact facebook this summer
was running a competition for
programmers i think
the the reward was something like 100
000 for the best
algorithm that recognizes hate memes so
recognize when an image is spreading
so-called hate speech
they had a whole competition for that so
they're very clearly out in the open
training their algorithms how to
recognize this kind of stuff obviously
they're not being very transparent about
it so we don't i would love to see what
kind of data facebook users or twitter
uses
to train its algorithm to recognize hate
speech
so that's the language analysis site
then there's the network analysis side
which is potentially even scarier
network analysis doesn't look at the
content of what's being posted
it looks at connections who's following
who who's linking to who
uh who's retweeting her etc etc that's
how silicon valley
identifies entire networks so again
baseball fans
they look at who's following the big
baseball accounts uh who's tweeting
about baseball and they use that to
create a
model of an entire network you can
imagine how they're doing that with hate
speech
so say facebook bands are right-wing i
say they ban laura luma paul joseph
watson people like that
that's not the end of the story people
think the bit the bands that you can see
in front of you the end of the story
they're not
that also sends a message to the
algorithm all of these millions of
accounts on facebook
we may not ban them but they were
following an account known for posting
hate speech they're sharing links to
infowars known for posting
disinformation conspiracy theories
uh then the language analysis will kick
in while they're saying hashtag
maga they're saying uh all sorts of
words that other
other accounts known for posting hate
speech post as well
so while they may not be in violation of
our hate speech policies
we should probably turn their quality
ranking down
so the really scary thing that these
silicon valley companies can do
is they have the ability to censor and
suppress
entire political movements entire
networks millions of people at the same
time and the algorithms
they can do it automatically uh now have
i
seen exactly how this all works no it is
what people inside silicon valley are
telling me for people inside who work
for twitter facebook and google are
telling me
uh we know they have the ability you can
google network analysis it's a
mainstream field all the tech platforms
use it
uh we know they have the ability and
they have the motive and there's no
oversight no law stopping them from
using it so why on earth wouldn't they
use it this
they have every reason to and no reason
not to
right and this is because the social
media companies are following the
mission
of political mission their moral mission
their values their own values and they
actually and this is the really scary
part is they actually program the
algorithms
with their political values
and in today's world when our political
tribes
aren't merely uh just sort of fellow
travelers with different opinions on
policy or interest rates or tax policy
or whatever
our tribes have been divided now by
moral compass
by religious fervor by evil
and good and dark versus light and it's
very clear that everyone on
the left believes that everyone on the
right
are not just incorrect with their policy
prescriptions but
actually bad human beings that
don't deserve fair treatment that don't
deserve a say that don't deserve a
conversation
just think listeners like how often your
own family members will just block you
on facebook or forget about you because
you voted for trump
there is a moral war happening and it's
now embedded
in the algorithms in the technology in
the programming
and if we don't do something about it
now
in the next two three four five ten
years
if some party the left if they get total
control of the government
and of our institutions and then the
algorithms themselves
there's going to come a moment at which
john rod calls this the dark
knight where the long night where the
first mover advantage in technology the
monopoly power around search and
algorithms and social media becomes some
impenetrable
it's something you will not be able to
escape from it is a
long and perpetual darkness that will be
cast upon this country and the entire
world and every citizen that's in it
we will not be able to speak to each
other
conduct financial transactions even just
send each other simple messages
much less do any activism or any uh you
know resistance
uh to use their term whatsoever and so
the urgency
around this issue couldn't be more
dire it couldn't be more severe this is
the time at which we need to do
something about it because this is the
time at which something can still be
done
it really scares the crap out of me to
think that
somebody who believes i am immoral
because i believe in the equality
of opportunity rather than the equality
of outcome
is going to be able to program me out of
existence i mean i experience it i'm
shadow band
i can tell when the algorithm has me
locked down or when it has me let free
i know that i'm not being seen i'm being
muted it happens everywhere and it
happens in search results it happens and
social media happens on twitter but we
persist
we persist today because we must because
this is going to get worse
so now that we are briefly on the long
night thing the
i'll tell you one thing that's possibly
even scarier than that
you won't it'll all be invisible we
won't even know that certain things are
being suppressed
keep in mind these tech platforms know
everything about us they know what goes
viral they're experts in what goes viral
so they
not only that are they not only do they
worry about these tech platforms
suppressing the current trump movement
as exist today
but what new movements are they
suppressing before they even gain
momentum do we even know
we don't know they could be nipping
movements in the bud because you know a
language analysis
has uh detected a threat to their to
their values and we wouldn't even know
about it
that's insane to me and you also
mentioned the two tribes i think this
will happen the anti-establishment left
as well there's a little bit about this
in the uh in the book as well
um facebook is advised by the atlantic
council
the atlanta council is a neoconservative
pro-war pro-intervention think tank um
certainly we can both remember when the
uh the anti-establishment left
and the anti-establishment right that
was the big divide over the iraq war
uh if facebook had been around during
the iraq war do you think they would
have suppressed the anti-establishment
left well they're being advised by the
atlantic council the atlanta council
probably would have told them to
so i think if bernie sanders supporters
and uh anti-establishment left-wingers
think this
power won't be used against them i think
it almost certainly will be
yeah and i think that that is why there
is some common resonance with some
bernie supporters and trump supporters
in my book democrats are deplorable i
i interviewed and profiled a couple of
bernie supporters who ended up voting
for trump and who by the way are not
returning to the democratic party
but there was an anti-establishment sort
of common thread between
uh bernie and and maga guys just sort of
a similar diagnosis
but a different prescription for how to
how to manage it
and uh you know i think unfortunately
that sort of commonality right now has
been squashed
whether it's been squashed naturally or
because they've isolated us into our
social media silos and don't allow cross
you know pollination they don't allow
collaboration
because you're right they do identify
these nodes and then they they
sort of uh put a barrier a silent
invisible barrier
up uh so when people say you're you're
in a
um a sound chamber an echo chamber
sometimes you're in one because
of your own choice but sometimes you're
in one because it's
outside of your control because you're
just put there and so this the stuff
that's scary
is overt but there's also covert actions
uh you know i was gonna ask you if
there's humans doing the technology or
if it's the tech that they created doing
start doing the censorship
it's clearly both humans it's both
humans and the technology that they
created
i mean there are instances in which
there are people manually
altering things manually closing down
accounts manually disconnecting people
from each other
what examples do you have of just you
know
individual human behavior people being
like i'm going to
change this i'm going to stop this i'm
going to silence these people
are there you can't even call them rogue
right because they have the support of
the companies but you know
is this like a handful of people doing
this are there people who are actively
i'm going to like pull this switch and
unfollow you from that guy which happens
to me all the time my good friends are
unfollowed from me people that would
never unfollow me ever in a million
years
they wake up one day and they're not
following me anymore on twitter
you know is there some human element
where they're literally picking and
choosing and doing things like that
well in the uh in the chapter on
facebook uh in the book
called deleted big text battle to erase
the trump movement and steal the
election
uh you'll find a discussion of the hate
agents list which we linked to breitbart
news
in part uh back in 2019 and the hate
the hate agents listings exactly as you
describe a manually curated list
of controversial people that facebook
considers controversial
high-profile political individuals that
facebook is monitoring
for potential hate speech of the people
who are on that list
uh laura luma paul joseph watson
eventually banned from the platform both
of them
uh candace owens was on the list for uh
future monitoring um
but there were a couple of left wingers
on the list linda sasso was on the list
as well
uh interestingly facebook concluded they
had little notes next to each name
with uh items that might be regarded as
hateful
um and uh first of all this this is this
is quite scary this is chilling they
weren't just monitoring
actions and statements that were made on
facebook but they were also monitoring
what people were doing off facebook
so uh one of the things next to paul
joseph watson's name was the fact that
he interviewed tommy robinson
uh which facebook who facebook considers
a hate figure
on his youtube account youtube isn't
owned by facebook uh they were
monitoring
australian senator fraser anning and one
of the items next to his name
was um the fact that he attended a rally
where certain far-right individuals were
also present
um and in linda sarsour's case they
noted
that off the platform she defended the
palestinian terrorist rasmaya oda
but facebook said that shouldn't be
locked as a hate signal so
uh i mean it's like portuguese wouldn't
get some trouble for interviewing
someone
but uh they let uh sarsour off the hook
for actually praising a
1970s terrorist so the the double
standards are clearly there
but it's interesting that they're
monitoring both sides of the aisle
they're murdering anti-assassins left
and anti-establishment right
i can certainly see a scenario in which
uh you know you see a big movement in
favor of a war like we saw the iraq war
we have the mainstream media on one side
and the anti-semite left on the other
side
where uh the focus shifts to censoring
the anti-sentiment left i could totally
see that happening especially when you
have the foreign policy establishment of
the atlantic council
so deeply embedded with the with uh with
facebook with these tech guides
yeah that does give some credence to the
argument at first they came for the
milos and you said nothing and now
all of a sudden you're just done right
it's like we have to stand up for these
principles because we all
actually deserve these principles and i
would for one support
anybody having a voice out there if only
so that they can be so obviously
discredited we can attack them we can
shout them down with the better ideas
but if we rely on pulling the trigger
silencing people basically beheading
them behind closed doors and black ops
and black op camps you know of
algorithms then you know it's gonna
they're gonna come for you
one day they're gonna come for me
they're gonna come for you know your mom
one day they're going up the new york
post newspaper
by alexander hamilton as they did last
week right that to me
is just mind-boggling i mean and even as
that story evolves
and no one denies the hunter biden
emails no one denies the hunter biden
crack or meth pipe or whatever picture
that he had
no one denies any of this stuff they
just start to say oh well you know we
don't like where it came from or
you know it's not it was planted by the
russians yeah right
come on with that you would think they
would get tired of that story or at
least come up with a better one at this
point but you're right
new york post remains in quarantine or
blacklisted or whatever
simply for posting a file an article the
day source the day fact check that with
original documents that have not
that have not been discredited and have
also been verified to some degree
this is a prime example of actually
just the truth or at least something
worth debating
as the truth or something worth
investigating as the truth
completely squashed but ironically
or you know unexpectedly i never know
when to use word irony anymore so
unexpectedly it's sort of that george
lakov notion of don't think of the
elephant
uh basically twitter and facebook were
like don't think of the hunter biden
photos
and that's what everybody wanted to talk
about and think about so that
that's a fascinating um example of what
happens when they do it
overtly it draws attention to it but
when they do it covertly
you don't even know it it's like the end
of sopranos you're just having lunch at
the diner with your family and all of a
sudden everything
goes silent you don't know you know
maybe you're still talking but you're
dead
you're dead you don't even know it what
are some of the scarier overt
things that you've seen i did some work
before
um with the news organization that we
all know that does investigative work
where i did some background information
on dr
epstein and i was looking at his work
and and and his analysis of google
search results and
his analysis of the predictive text
that they give you in the search bar uh
and the things that he uncovered there
were terrifying the way that they feed
you
suggestions based on what they want you
to think and they hide suggestions based
on what they don't want you to think
they flash things up in front of your
eyes
for a brief second and then take it down
using subliminal messaging to persuade
you and coerce you
what are some of the scariest overt
things that you have seen
and maybe if there's any way that we can
be more aware of them so that we can
identify them because that to me is the
scariest part it's the
silent killer what i would recommend
everyone do is whenever there's like a
big controversial news story in the news
you can
test this yourself try comparing
different search results try comparing
google
to bing and yahoo and dot dot go uh try
uh
seeing how often a breitbart news link
will appear on those other search
engines versus google
uh we certainly saw this with with uh
black lives matter recently we did a
story at breitbart
uh the search suggestions for black
lives matter on um
on google were completely sanitized no
negative suggestions at all
on the other search engines they they
reflected what people were searching for
so
is black lives matter marxist his black
lives matter terrorist organization
as well as some other more positive uh
suggestions as well so it was a mix of
both
on google completely sanitized and i'm
convinced they do this with almost
anything
and actually one of the things i want to
do off this podcast is have a look for
the
suggestions on how to buy and that'll be
an interesting one to uh to look into
um oh by the way on that point you
mentioned how uh how the response to the
hunter biden story was so blatant and so
obvious
uh my favorite one was snopes this uh
left-wing fact-checker
they are they fact-checked the picture
of hunter biden in bed with his with his
meth pipe and the fact check is
the picture is rated false because with
a big red false
uh marker saying uh people are saying
this is a picture of hunter biden in bed
with uh
with a crack pipe it's actually a meth
pipe and uh i got i gotta check into
that see if it's real i wouldn't be
surprised if someone if someone just did
that as a parody but if it's real it's
so hilarious well it's believable which
means the critique the critique
hits home that's for sure
um but as you said that actually ended
up amplifying the story i think there
was a
study out today showing that uh people
shared the new york post story twice
as much on these platforms after the
censorship than
than before uh but worth keeping in mind
that doesn't happen
to everyone when the smaller accounts
get censored when the accounts that
don't have links to conservative media
get censored oftentimes people just
don't find out about it ever
uh that's really important but there was
an account just here just the other
uh day an account with i think 900 000
followers
just an account run by uh you know maga
supporting mom i think in
india in the midwest or uh somewhere
like that
nine hundred thousand followers should
build it over a period of ten years
and suddenly taken away because you know
trump i imagine
so many times it happens to people in
the grassroots and no one finds out
about it because
you know not as big as the new york post
not as big as as big of a deal but it
happens every day
for so many people yeah i mean there's
different strategies for different
people who have different
goals and intents out of social media if
you're just an individual citizen
and you're using your real name i really
strongly advise you to just sort of
just just read read and read and just
don't try
just don't stick your head out on the
chopping block because they're gonna
come for you or they're gonna silence
you or quarantine you or
or wall you all from the rest of the
world or in worst case scenario somebody
out there is gonna
pick up on something you said and use it
to silence you and get you canceled like
they did to me
but if you're somebody a social media
professional you know the only real
um the only real strategy that makes any
sense is just to be on as many platforms
as you possibly can
and then to also build your own internal
email lists and your own internal
contacts and databases and own networks
like we've done with the liminal order
we've built our own private network off
of social media that cannot be cancelled
cannot be silenced
we're connected in multiple different
ways there's no way to cut us off so
we've now
300 guys we're probably gonna have a
thousand guys by the end of next year
and we will not be silenced and we will
not be cut off from the rest of the
world
but that is a real fear for people and i
gotta tell you here i am building up a
youtube channel and i still wonder every
day if it's just gonna get
you know dragged out from underneath my
feet so i have to just keep pushing and
keep pushing things on all different
platforms
one of the other things that you talked
about in the book which i've found to be
really terrifying is the financial
blacklist because this goes beyond
just you know hey you don't have access
to social media big whoop you can't post
a tweet about your cats who cares about
that that's not a big deal
but let's talk about what happens when
you can't even access the financial
system
also keep in mind that there is a
continued push and effort to move us
away
from cash transactions and exclusively
into electronic transactions that all
run
on the back of the visa and mastercard
and whatever network so
talk to me about the financial blacklist
because the social media stuff is just
one element of the way that people are
being censored controlled and deleted by
big tech it's not just
i love how the title isn't social media
companies
or twitter or youtube no it's big tech
it's tech in every element of your life
and so this is a different angle to that
tell us about the scary part of
financial blacklisting
so uh e-commerce and you know online
fundraising was another
thing about big tech that was very
threatening to the establishment it was
why ron paul was able to be so
successful in 2008 and 2012
totally outraged his establishment
opponents just by using the
mainly by using the internet uh but this
has been
this is being shut down as well gofundme
banning conservative fundraising
campaigns
uh i believe they i believe they shot
down it was one of the crowdfunding
platforms that shot down
a fundraiser for kyle rittenhouse's uh
legal fund but they let the one
for uh the guy doloff who shot who shot
a uh
a conservative activist in uh denver
then it allowed that one to stay up
so again you see the double standards
patreon as well kicked off so many
people
kicked up lauren sutherland kicked off
sargon of akkad uh you can't use that
anymore
but also it goes further the credit card
companies visa mastercard
uh gab still has no access to i believe
they still have no access to uh
to uh credit card transactions having a
few other people to david horowitz
um robert uh
uh who's the other guy the two big
island critics
there's david horowitz and there's
robert spencer
so uh yeah again they got caught up by
by the credit card systems as well i
think horowitz eventually
got it back um but again
there's no law stopping them from doing
this they can pull
services for any reason and this didn't
used to be a problem because why on
earth would a credit card company cut
you off for your political opinions
but now it's becoming a distinct
possibility we have now left-wing
pressure groups operating today
putting ceaseless pressure on mastercard
on visa on all the on the entire
financial sector
to start denying service to people for
political reasons
that's something they wanted something
they're pushing for they haven't really
got it yet
to the extent that they've got it with
the uh with the tech companies with the
tech fundraising platforms like patreon
and gofundme
um and you know institutions like chase
banks strongly deny
uh ever censoring people politically
even though some people say that's what
they're doing
uh leader of the proud wars i think said
his chase bank account was cut off the
other people said so as well
uh trace denies it um
the other financial institutions are
pushing back a little bit they haven't
made any
they haven't made some of the moves that
these left ring activist organists have
demanded
they've made like establish a so-called
human rights council at mastercard
to monitor the people who use their uh
their
services and cut them off if needed they
haven't done that yet but it's what they
want it's what they're pushing for
and uh that is that is truly terrifying
because you're in
that will control everyone's entire
livelihood as you say we're moving away
from the uh the cash economy to a
entirely digital economy the only one
glimmer of hope recently is the coinbase
ceo who recently came out and said well
we're not going to be a political
company we're not going to do virtue
signaling i don't think he used that
word exactly but basically says
we're just going to do financial
transactions cryptocoin transactions
that's all we do
we're not getting involved in politics
and immediately 40 or 50
um social justice warriors at the
company immediately resigned which is
great by the way he uh that's a huge win
for coinbase in my view so that's a
glimmer of hope that the crypto economy
yeah yes you're absolutely right
financial censorship is real and growing
it is terrifying it is another
sort of tightening of the noose around
people that have
different opinions and different
political views and again i want to
bring this back to the core
50 100 years ago there was not the
motivation
to behave like this because our
political differences
were not seen as moral failings and
moral differences separated by
religious-like belief systems
that paints the other person as evil and
sub-human
and not worthy of the rights that we all
have in the united states
and so because we have the moral compass
of intersectionality critical race
theory
radical feminism or even just regular
old feminism
driving these issues and driving the
algorithms
they've captured the c-level executives
they've captured all of the
incoming entry-level people because
they're all coming out of college
understanding and believing that
everybody who opposes them or doesn't
believe in rape culture who doesn't
believe that everybody
every girl on campus is sexually
assaulted or doesn't believe that
women get paid less than men for the
same exact work with the same exact
qualifications
that anyone that doesn't believe any of
this stuff is
evil horrible person doesn't even
believe doesn't even
deserve to communicate to commune
to have news to have financial services
and so
it's basically exile this is an internal
exile and it's being driven by this
moral
underpinning intersectionality critical
race theory so it becomes
this tech solution we can band-aid it up
we can regulate it in the right ways we
can file lawsuits and do anti-trust and
whatnot
but until the ideology is dead until
this this this good versus evil thing is
finished until they stop
thinking honestly in their hearts that
we're all hitler's you know they're
going to continue to find ways to try to
delete us silence us
squash us and if they can't do that what
else do they do
they have proactive measures too right
there's sort of like a whole defamation
posse out there there's
there's you call the defamation engine
if they can't just cut you off
then they're going to start smearing you
like tell me about that because that
that's a proactive measure that that is
seemingly
very disgusting to me destroying
people's reputation this is the uh
uh again you know one of the scariest
chapters in the book that i wrote
uh if you want to find the book by the
way it's at deletedbook.com there are a
number of places you can buy
from barnes and noble amazon all major
retailers
but the defamation engine this is the
way that uh
you know the first half of the book
discusses how
uh big tech was a massive boost for
freedom
uh well not big tech but the internet in
general was a massive boost for freedom
uh and generally a good thing that they
tried to take away after the election
but one way in which even the original
incident was not particularly good for
freedom
even the uncensored internet was because
it empowered
cancer culture it almost created council
culture
because uh before the internet when
there was like a scandal about someone
first of all scandals usually only
affected celebrities and politicians
who spend their entire careers preparing
for it second of all you know it's on
the news for a day or two in the
newspapers for a day or two
then you know the newspaper gets thrown
away the the cable anchor moves on to a
different topic
so scandals are not last for eternity
but in the online
era that's completely flipped on its
head first of all
it affects everyone not just celebrities
anyone can get canceled anyone can be
written about in a blog
or talked about in a youtube video video
whether you're prepared for it or not
whether you're a public figure or not
has happened to so many people
and it's not limited by time people
don't just forget about it because it's
then on your google search
history forever it's a permanent scarlet
letter
and google empowers this by empowering
wikipedia
wikipedia i think is the platform that
least deserves section 230 protection
because it's not just a publisher
but the most powerful publisher in the
world more has more power to smear
someone's reputation
more power to smear an organization's
reputation than any other company
because wikipedia results are always at
the top of google
almost every search you'll find them
right up there
um they've submitted so many people
they've spared breitbart news
uh they smeared trump mark levin sean
hannity and anyone you can
anybody can think of on the right
because wikipedia is controlled by a
tight circle of far left editors
um but uh to go back to you know the way
the media operates today there's no
time limit to the media there's no
morning edition and evening edition of
the newspaper it's 24
7. uh there's a limitless space on the
internet there's a need to publish
publish publish more and more and more
more material so you've got so many
journalists now are simply dedicated to
ruining the reputations
of their political opponents that's how
they get clicks that's how they make
their living it's really disgraceful
actually i can't i can't imagine people
who make their living doing that
but it's so powerful now because it
stays on your google results forever it
goes into wikipedia
wikipedia determines who's going to be
an authoritative source
and the sources they decide are
authoritative are sources like the daily
beast
like the washington post who
increasingly thrive
off of ruining people's reputation of
smearing people
like the covington kids like anyone you
can think of
and the people challenging those
narratives breitbart news the daily
caller who might stick up with you and
defend you if you get defamed
banned on wikipedia you can't use them
as authoritative sources
so that's what i call the defamation
engine in the book it's a
it's the it's the alliance of
you know the media the new media the
digital media
wikipedia and google that's true that's
such an important component of cancel
culture
and we're really gonna take section 230
away from wikipedia
that site more than any other tech giant
deserves to be sued for defamation
i agree and what you've described about
this
media environment where an
article can get posted then it gets
reposted then it gets
cited and these things take on a life of
their own because
out and i've lived this i know this
firsthand experience
i got doxxed in 2018 i got smeared i got
called a nazi on
you know unjustifiably so obviously and
what happened was is that then you get
people like judd legume who was that
think progress before
and they would just they just turn out
the worst kind of slander and the worst
kind of activism and then
then like 50 other repeater bloggers
take that post they quote it they talk
about it
then a thousand other repeater bloggers
just repeat those
and i called them chum bloggers right
there's like blood in the water so they
just
turn it up they turn that that chum up
and they and
and then all of a sudden one piece turns
into 50 pieces
and then you type in your name and all
of a sudden the first eight pages of
your name
search is all based on this one piece of
crap lie put forth by an
activist who doesn't care if you live or
die or your kids go hungry or you can
coach your dad your
son's a little league game or if it's
right or wrong or whatever
and then all these psychopaths and sick
of fans pile on and then they post 50
other things and all of a sudden
your search is just overwhelmed you're
just completely overwhelmed and so i
experienced this reputation death
right like i used to work in education i
helped the poorest
least advantaged american kids in my
city get better educations i was a
charter school turnaround
expert i dedicated my life to helping
black kids get better educations and
closing the achievement gap
and one day an activist an antifa
activist decides to call me a nazi
think progress amplifies it a thousand
chum bloggers repeat it
and now you search my name and it's just
you know nazi racist
hates kids and that is just the end of
it for me in education because
i'm an executive i'm executive director
ceo level
so when somebody's going to hire me at
least they're going to do a curse
research on
on social media they're going to google
my name they're going to do some
research so forget about the fact that
it just
that news spread through my entire
network instantaneously
totally false information that first
mover advantage in people's brains
it was lodged in their heads it's very
difficult to dislodge afterwards
my reputation completely incinerated
within five seconds
and there's nothing i can do about it no
matter how many times i publish things
or say
that i did that wasn't me or what it
doesn't matter it's as if my resume
is written for me by somebody else and
delivered to every possible employer
before
i get there and on the resume it says
don't hire me i'm a nazi
this is insanity we have to figure out a
way to fix this problem
because i am the lucky one i took that
energy i turned it around into something
positive and now it's fueled me
in my all of my media work and i'm
spreading the good message and having a
positive impact on the world
but there are guys whose first name is
the worst the first name
search is the worst thing they ever did
by accident they can't get a job
and then you find them dead in their car
two years later and their family hasn't
heard from them for six months this
happens
it happens to people that don't have a
voice and don't have a platform and
aren't as fortunate as i am
so this is a matter of life and death
this isn't a matter of
oh you want to have fun on the internet
no this is life or death
your entire professional career is at
risk if you get slandered
repeated and google pasted for the rest
of your life
there's no appeal process there's no
anybody to talk to about it
and even if you could reach them they
don't care
they don't care and so this is a major
issue and i want people to understand
it's not just corporations not just big
media players it's not just websites
like breitbart
it's not even somebody like me who had
the ability to turn it around it's for
everyday average americans if you want
to talk to your friends
your family get news information conduct
financial transactions have a reputation
we live in an information world in fact
what i said is we recently we live in a
story economy
and you have to tell your own story
because if you don't tell your own story
someone else is going to do it
and now they won't even let you tell
your story and they'll tell your story
for you so this is a very bleak
scenario unfortunately a lot of the
topics i've covered lately haven't been
super uplifting and that's because
we are looking into precipice of
something very awful
long night when the algorithms take over
fueled and and
inspired by this you know
intersectionality that's taken over all
of our institutions
and so i project one glimmer of hope
into the whole cancel culture thing and
by the way i think there's a certain
point i did i didn't just do one chapter
on it about the defamation we did two
chapters on it
because the second part of this is the
uh what i call the worldwide honeypot
yeah so not only are reputations of
greater risk than ever before
as you say not just big people not
celebrities pollution but everyone every
individual
but we're also incentivized by social
media platforms
to post everything about ourselves on
social media
all our embarrassing college moments
online forever
so at the very moment when this cancel
control is emerging we're also being
encouraged to
have zero privacy and you know expose
all our personal lives all our opinions
our craziest opinions stupid opinions
stupid jokes we might made when we were
younger
we're encouraged to post that all online
to a global audience
so it's those both things it's the uh
the defamation and the uh
and the honey pot of social media which
encourages this you know this culture of
expression
but also compromises everyone in the
process
uh but here's here's a glimmer of hope
because there's so much of it now
because this council culture
industry has grown to such an
extraordinary degree
i've noticed it starting to have
diminishing returns i mean how many
people have they tried to cancel over
the past year and just completely failed
uh they did these they've done these
massive massive stories about people
like jack the soviet
uh michelle mulkin uh there was a
documentary right now by some random
dude i never heard about the atlantic no
one paid attention to it
um and that guy spent years pretending
to be friends with right wingers worming
his way into their circles to get all
these stories
yes working this no one's paying
attention to it dad
and after daniel i know he was
no it's paying attention to it they
tried to cancel peter thiel no one paid
attention to that either there was a
massive buzzfeed story
about him palling around with so-called
white nationalists no one cared
uh jack berserberg again you know he's
retweeted by the president to this day
no one cared when they tried to cancel
her
michelle mulkin they tried to cancel her
even establishment conservatives tried
to cancel her
she got a gig at newsmax a few weeks
after that
so that didn't work either uh so the the
glimmer of hope is that there's so much
of this now people just so sick of
it they don't care you know you call
people nazis you call people racist you
call people white supremacists no one's
paying attention they just
assume it's all [ __ ] which 99 of it
is
yeah indeed uh this is a phenomenon that
i first read about
uh with jordan hall and john robb
talking about the blue church
and their you know sort of scorched
earth policy of calling everyone racist
nazi bigoted whatever and eventually
you use that term enough you kill enough
people
that all that are remaining are people
who are
resistant to the kind of name calling
who are resistant like like
you know have a antibiotic resistance
almost to to that kind of name calling
we're inoculated we can't be impacted
and so you're left with people that are
actually really quite strong
and left with people who are resistant
to that kind of stuff i know in 2018 i
was a
at that time when i called like a
civilian i wasn't a public figure i was
and i got destroyed but i have seen a
trend change and like you said in which
people are taking that less seriously
and sometimes i wonder if i'm like the
last casualty in vietnam
i mean i hate i don't want to see it
happen to anybody else of course
but they did really destroy my life and
i'm glad to see a little bit of hope
a little bit of hope there whereas
people are just starting to take it less
seriously and totally discount it
now my last question to you is we try to
wrap this up here and the book again
is deleted big text battle to erase the
trump movement and steal the election
you can get it right now
on amazon you can get it at barnes noble
you can get it at another of other
places also
follow along here at libertarian blue
on twitter make sure you follow him
there and get the book because we go and
he goes into much greater detail on all
this and in a great format he's a
tremendous writer
what the last question here is what are
we going to do
what do we do what do we do as citizens
what do we do as a government what do we
do as political
players what do we do as customers of
these social media
are are we the customers or we are we
the products what do we do as the
products
of these social media companies like how
how do we handle this what do we do over
the next couple of years
uh first of all stop using google
immediately there's no reason to use
google
over the other search engines uh second
of all while i wouldn't recommend
uh removing yourself from facebook or
twitter or youtube because then you're
essentially self-censoring yourself
you should also as you say have
presences on all the other smaller
platforms as well
bit shoot um uh
parlor gab all of these platforms um
on a political level the the real danger
of social media manipulation is what
they're doing to undecided voters we
we know we kind of have a sense that
we're being propagandized as you know
conservatives or free speech defenders
on social media but we have no idea what
they're showing to undecided voters
it's probably all propaganda um so make
sure
around election season talk to undecided
voters don't just devote
all your attention your energies to
social media actually talk to people in
real life get the message out there
at least until big tech is brought under
control
as to bringing them under control we've
got to push for one thing
one thing only i think this is the bit
the most easy fix you can do
the simplest legislative pick some
people talking about you know establish
a huge bureaucracy to make sure they
stay uh
these platforms stay neutral i think
what you're going to do is say you know
if you want
section 230 protections the definition
of being a platform is that you don't
moderate content you don't filter
content that's legal that's constitution
protected
on behalf of your users you can create
tools to filter certain types of content
but you have to give users the option if
you prove that they opted into that they
chose to be subject to those filters
that's critical that's what we need to
push for
and republicans especially but whoever
your representative is
has to know that if you're taking money
from big tech that's just completely
unacceptable
just primary those [ __ ] it needs to
be as unacceptable or more unacceptable
frankly
than uh taking money from planned
parenthood would be to a social
conservative
that's how unacceptable it should be
lastly
uh it's really the executive branch the
presidential election could not be more
important
uh because the executive branch as far
as i can tell is the only
branch of the government that's actually
serious about tackling the problem at
the moment it's the doj
that's just filed an anti-trust case
against google it's the fcc
chairman now talking about looking at
changes to section 230.
so uh really this particular election is
huge
uh get involved in that whatever you do
because
this is you know do we want digital
totalitarianism or do we want
a executive branch that will actually
try uh and bring these tech giants under
control that is absolutely critical
that's what i'm saying
we are on the edge of digital
totalitarianism the long
night approaches if we don't do
something about it now i can't stress
enough how the first mover advantage
here is going to be critical
if the political powers are aligned with
the corporate tech powers and the
algorithms and the financial companies
and wikipedia
and they decide that it's over for all
of us and they create their own social
credit score that's not just hidden
beneath the algorithms but
is even more upfront and obvious we all
are in for a very long
struggle just ask the people of hong
kong the pro-democracy people in hong
kong what it's like now
to be under the heel of the chinese
totalitarian credit scoring system their
use of big tech
facial recognition travel limitations
etc
black mirror is coming i wish i were
exaggerating i wish i were being
alex jones tim foil hat here but i'm not
it's all right in front of us the facts
are clear as day the trend
is clear and flowing unabated
we have to do something elum you're
working on that
you have put out a fantastic book it's
called deleted
big tech not just social media mind you
guys big
tax battle to erase the trump movement
and steal the election and you know what
it's not even just a trump movement
it's just it's it's to silence all of us
anyone that descends from the
intersectionality critical race theory
perspective which is a lot of people
it is a lot of people and if we're going
to you know avoid the tyranny of the
minority here we have to do something so
get out and vote
drag a friend to vote with you coming up
on november 3rd drag free threads three
three friends and make it happen alum is
a pleasure to speak with you as always
the senior tech correspondent from
breitbart news
follow him on twitter as long as they'll
have him
at libertarian blue get the book it's
called deleted
thank you so much buddy i really
appreciate it and let's touch base again
after the election
thanks jack this is awesome all right my
pleasure talk to you soon bye